Guide to the Angier Biddle Duke Papers, 1923-1990s and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Angier Biddle Duke papers 1923-1990s and undated
Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995
93.0 linear feet Extent: 45,866 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
dukeab
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Some use restrictions apply, but the collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Angier Biddle Duke, Chief of Protocol and ambassador to Spain and Denmark under the Kennedy and Johnson administrations, were initially assembled in 1973. Continued donations through 1995 brought the collection to its present size and scope.
Biographical Note
1915 Born in New York City, Nov. 30. Son of Angier Buchanan and Cordelia (Biddle) Duke
1934-1937 Attended Yale University
1937 Married first wife, Priscilla St. George. Had one son by her, Angier Pony St. George Duke (b. 1938)
1939 Divorced Priscilla St. George
1940 Married Margaret Screven White
1940-1945 Served from private to major in U. S. Army
1945 Officer in charge of Air Transport Command, Paris section
1945-1948 President, Duke International Corporation, NYC
1949 Appointed to U.S. Foreign Service
1949 Appointed to post in American Embassy, Buenos Aires, Argentina
1951 Special Assistant to Ambassador, American embassy, Madrid, Spain
1952 Divorced Margaret Screven White
1952 Married Maria-Luisa de Aranha, Dec. 11. Had two children by her: Maria Luisa (Marylou) Biddle Duke (b. 1954) and Dario Drexel Duke (b. 1957)
1952-1953 U.S. Ambassador to El Salvador (youngest ambassador in US at 36 years old)
1954-1960 President, International Rescue Commission
1955-1961 Commissioner, Long Island State Park
1957 Received LL. D., Iona College
1958-1960 V.P. of CARE
1961 Maria-Luisa killed in airplane crash, Queens, NY, on her way to her daughter's birthday party
1961-1965 Chief of protocol, Dept. of State, Kennedy and Johnson administrations
1962 Married Robin Chandler Lynn, May 12. Had one son by her, Angier Biddle Duke, Jr. (b. 1963)
1965-1968 Ambassador to Spain.
1968 Chief of protocol, Dept. of State
1968-1969 Ambassador to Denmark
1969 LL. D., Duke University
1973-1976 Commissioner of Civic Affairs and Public Events, NYC
1974-1995 Director, Appeal of Conscience Foundation
1976-1977 Chairman, NYC Democratic Committee
1977-1979 President, The Spanish Institute, NYC (chairman, 1983-1987)
1978-1979 Chairman, NY State Council on Ethnic Affairs President, Nat'l. Committee on American Foreign Policy, Inc.
1979-1981 Ambassador to Morocco
1981-1990 Trustee, Long Island University
1981-1986 Chairman, U.S.-Japan Foundation, NYC
1981-1995 Chairman, World Affairs Council, Long Island
1986-1990 Chancellor, Long Island University, Southampton Campus
1988-1995 Chairman, Duke Family Association of NC
1992-1995 President, Council of American Ambassadors
1995 Died, Southampton, Long Island
Collection Overview
The papers of Angier Biddle Duke span the years 1915 to 1995, though the bulk of the collection ranges from 1940 to 1995. The papers chiefly consist of correspondence; scrapbooks; diaries; photographs; diplomatic papers; sound recordings, video cassette tapes and films; appointment books; clippings; printed material; and business papers. There are also a few legal and financial papers. Miscellaneous materials also include writings by other authors; fiscal and other reports; school grade reports; invitations; guest lists; and some memorabilia. The collection documents Angier Biddle Duke's long career in politics and diplomacy, as well as his activities as chairman or president of various agencies and institutions. Much of the material also documents Duke's personal life as well as the social and political activities of various family members. The subjects represented in greatest detail include U.S. politics and foreign policy; the Kennedy and Johnson administrations; and the history of US. and foreign diplomacy. In addition, the papers contain valuable information on economic and social conditions in Spain, Morocco, Denmark, Africa, Pakistan, and other countries; World War II; post-World War Europe; European and Pakistani refugees; civil rights and de-segregation (especially in Washington, DC); philanthropy; Long Island social life and communities; and the Duke, Biddle, and Drexel families.
Details on Angier Biddle Duke's life as well as information on the Duke, Biddle, and Drexel families can be found in the Biographical Data Series. These materials include some of A. B. Duke's military records; articles on A. B. Duke; biographical entries on A. B. Duke from Who's Who and Biography Today; "in memoriam" booklets from his first wife's funeral and the funeral of Angier Buchanan Duke, A. B. Duke's father; and genealogical materials on the families. Selected condolences out of the hundreds sent to Robin Chandler Duke after her husband's death in 1995 also reveal much about the personality and life of A. B. Duke. In addition, the narratives in the Diaries Series offer a great deal of material concerning the personalities of A. B. Duke and his family and acquaintances throughout his life.
The Correspondence Series also offers details on the personal relations between members of the Duke, Biddle, Semans, and Trent families, though correspondence between immediate family members makes up a relatively small percentage of this large series. The correspondence files are therefore perhaps most useful for the documentation they provide about A. B. Duke's extraordinary career and his many important friends and contacts in international politics and high society. Additional biographical data on A. B. Duke and family members, particularly useful for information on Robin Chandler Duke's social and political activities, can be found in the Clippings Series files.
The Pictures Series contains hundreds of photographs of the Duke, Semans, and Biddle families. Some early photographs of Angier Biddle Duke were taken during his enlistment in the Army from 1940-1945. An album entitled "A celebration of the life of Benjamin Newton Duke, 1979" can be found in the Scrapbooks Series. Finally, as A. B. Duke served as president of the Duke Family Association of NC from 1988-1995, there are a number of items related to the meetings of this genealogical association found in the Correspondence Series.
Angier Biddle Duke was best known for his ambassadorial skills and his political acumen beginning with his appointment to the office of Ambassador to El Salvador in 1952 as the youngest ambassador ever appointed to a post. His subsequent career in diplomacy and politics, including his appointment as Chief of Protocol under Presidents Kennedy and Johnson, is unusually well-documented through the Correspondence Series, the Diaries Series, containing detailed personal diaries and memoirs; the Interviews Series (both taped and written); numerous scrapbooks and photographs found in the Scrapbooks and Pictures Series, the Printed Materials Series, which includes many articles on A. B. Duke; and the Clippings Series. A series of written and taped diaries entitled the "Ambassador's Diary" are especially interesting for A. B. Duke's candid reflections on his diplomatic experiences. A few items also reveal the family's experiences in foreign countries as viewed by his wife, Robin Chandler Duke, as exemplified by her brief diary from Brazil, Peru, and Bolivia (1976). A relatively minor source of information on the Dukes' itineraries include the Travel Series, which contains routine documents relating to the Dukes' travel activities. Other materials concerning foreign policy and diplomacy may be found in the Miscellaneous Series, where many articles and speeches by other authors are filed.
The political and social events of the 1960s and 1970s are well-represented in the A. B. Duke Papers in the multimedia formats associated with the Audio, Film, and Videotape Series, containing numerous recordings, audio and visual, of speeches, toasts, and visits of foreign dignitaries; the Scrapbooks and Pictures Series, which hold many candid and formal photographs of well-known politicians, diplomats, celebrities, and artists, many of them signed; and the Clippings Series, documenting many major world events as well as personal events from 1950s to the 1990s. One scrapbook covers President Kennedy's trip to Berlin, West Germany; another oversize scrapbook covers an international incident at Palomares, Spain (1966): while Duke was that country's ambassador, an undetonated US nuclear bomb was lost off the coast of Spain, then recovered after much consternation, and increased international outcry against nuclear weapons. Materials in the Protocol Papers Series also concern Kennedy's assassination and the transition to a Johnson White House during the period when A. B. Duke was Chief of Protocol. As Jacqueline Kennedy had already become a good friend of A. B. Duke's family, there are items in the Correspondence Series reflecting her close relationship with them in the difficult years after her husband's assassination.
The head of the State Department Office of Protocol serves as principal adviser to the President and Secretary of State on matters of diplomatic procedures governed by law or international customs and practice. Angier Biddle Duke's responsibilities as Chief of Protocol from 1961-65 and 1968, including his role in the arrangements for the Kennedy funeral, are best represented by materials in the Protocol Papers Series, arranged alphabetically by country, and by many valuable letters and telegrams in the Correspondence Series, and in the Writings and Speeches Series. In addition, a great deal of relevant information, both contemporary and retrospective in nature, can be found in the Interviews Series. Several important volumes in the Scrapbooks and Diaries Series are also were created as records of his tenure as Chief of Protocol, and the Pictures Series contains many candid and formal photographs during this period. Finally, events relating to the Office of Protocol are found in audio or film format in the Audio, Film, and Video Series. Memorabilia from this period such as invitations, dinner menus, guest lists, and souvenir programs from inaugurations abroad can also be found in the Miscellaneous Series.
A. B. Duke's extensive organizational activities in later decades are documented in greatest detail through the Correspondence, Subject Files, Interviews, Printed Materials, and Writings and Speeches Series. A large number of materials reflect A. B. Duke's long involvement in the administration of Long Island University, near his family residence in Southampton, N.Y., as well as in other institutions such as the International Rescue Commission, various Democratic committees, CARE, the NYC Dept. of Civic Affairs and Public Events, the Spanish Institute, the Appeal to Conscience Foundation, the Japan-American Institute, the World Affairs Council, and the American Council of Ambassadors, and many others with whom he was affiliated for shorter periods of time. The Subject Files and other series also illustrate A. B. Duke's later involvement in organizations attempting to establish more democratic structures in countries such as El Salvador, Nicaragua, and Guyana. Some materials also reflect Robin Chandler Duke's later involvement in politics, including her unsuccessful bid for the Democratic nomination to fill Koch's congressional seat in 1978, and her role as chairwoman of Population Action International.
Although they contain relatively few documents, the Legal and Financial Papers do provide some information on A. B. Duke's income and financial activities, and the Doris Duke Trust; also in the legal papers is a publisher's contract for the biography of Doris Duke and a copy of Angier Buchanan Duke's will. Other legal and financial matters related to the Duke and Biddle families, particularly the Doris Duke estate (1995) are referred to on a regular basis in the Correspondence Series. Very little is to be found in the collection on the administration, maintenance, or acquisition of Angier Biddle Duke's residences in Washington, NYC, or Long Island, though some illustrations of residences can be found in the Clippings and Pictures Series.
Collections in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library which contain information relevant to the Angier Biddle Duke Papers include the James Buchanan Duke Papers and especially the Semans Family Papers. The Duke University Living History Program collection, also in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, contains an interview with Angier Biddle Duke recorded in the 1970s.
Contents of Collection
- Biographical Data Series, 1923-1980s (bulk 1970s-1980s), (3 folders)
  Primarily biographical sketches and articles on Angier Biddle Duke, a few military records, "in memoriam" booklets for his first wife, Maria-Luisa de Aranha Duke and Angier Buchanan Duke, his father (d. 1923), and genealogical material and other information on the Duke, Semans, Drexel, and Biddle families, including some photocopies of early Duke family photographs. Also contains a group photograph of Semans and Trent family members.
  - Biographical data (Box 1)
- Financial Papers Series, ca. 1970s-1990s, (3 folders)
  Personnel records, tax statements, receipts, itemized expenses, and schedules of campaign contributions by A. B. Duke.
  - Financial papers (Box 1)
- Legal Papers Series, ca. 1970s-1980s, (3 folders)
  Publisher's contract related to Doris Duke biography, document related to the Doris Duke Trust (1978), and documents from a 1978 lawsuit involving "Pony" Duke. Also includes a copy of Angier Buchanan Duke's will (1928).
  - Legal papers (Box 1)
- Interviews Series, ca. 1960s-1980s, (8 folders)
  Transcripts of interviews given by Angier Biddle Duke. There are also a few interviews given by Brzezinski and several ambassadors. Some of the tapes are in the Audio, Film, and Video Series. Interviews are in rough date order. One lengthy interview of A. B. Duke (only titled as "Interview 51," circa 1980) is particularly rich in details on his personal and professional life.
  - Interviews (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1925-1995 (bulk 1960s-1995)
  Letters, photocopies and carbon copies of letters, telegrams, faxes, some invitations, and condolences. Correspondents include A. B. Duke, members of his immediate family, other relatives and friends, and well-known political figures and celebrities. Some of the correspondents include President Lyndon Johnson, Jacqueline Kennedy, Edward M. Kennedy, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., Cyrus Sulzberger, Adlai Stevenson, Coretta Scott King, Henry Ford II, Richard Nixon, Hubert Humphrey, Dean Rusk, Cyrus Vance, Prime Minister James Callahan, Albert Gore, Jimmy Carter, Jay Rutherfurd, Walter Annenberg, and many prominent ambassadors. Many are condolences on the sudden death of A. B. Duke's wife, Maria-Luisa de Aranha Duke in 1962, and many are congratulations offered upon his appointments to prominent positions. There are also many condolences sent to Robin Chandler Duke after A. B. Duke's death in 1995.
  Arranged chronologically, with some overlap of materials covering later decades.
  - 1925-1960; also has one folder of photocopies of letters relating to Duke's involvement with Kennedy family from 1961-1969. (Box 2)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 4)
  - 1966-1969 (Box 5)
  - 1970-1975 (Box 6)
  - 1975-1979 (Box 7)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - 1980-1982 (Box 9)
  - 1981-1985 (Box 10)
  - 1976-1990 (bulk 1986-1990) (Box 11)
  - 1972-1994 (bulk 1990-1994) (Box 12)
  - 1980-1994 (bulk 1989-1994) (Box 13)
  - 1974-1995 (Box 14)
  - 1994-1995 (chiefly condolences to his wife on A. B. Duke's death) (Box 15)
  - 1995 (chiefly condolences) (Box 16)
  - 1963-1995 (bulk 1995; chiefly condolences) (Box 17)
- Diaries Series, 1938-1992 (bulk 1961-1988)
  Diaries, memoirs, and journals in several formats ranging from handwritten volumes, handwritten sheets, typed drafts, transcripts of tapes, and audio cassettes. Some of the audio tapes are micro-cassettes; A. B. Duke's hand-held dictation recorder is located with the materials.
  [Originals closed to use. Staff must arrange to have use copies made before materials can be accessed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this collection.]
  - Chief of Protocol, 1961-1964 (Box 18)
  - US. Ambassador to Spain, 1966-1965 (2 vols.)
  - 1956, n.d. (2 vols.)
  - 1938-1940
  - Transcripts
    - n.d., (3 folders)
    - Mrs. Angier Biddle Duke: Notes from Brazil, Bolivia and Peru, 1976, Apr.
  - Tapes, n.d. (4 vols.)
  - Tapes, n.d. (6 vols.) (Box 19)
  - 1971-1982, (3 folders)
  - 1941-1967 (12 folders, 1 vol.) (Box 20)
  - 1941-1967 Audiocassettes (Master Tapes) (Box 20A)
  - 1941-1967 Audiocassettes (Use Tapes copy 1) (Box 20B)
  - 1941-1967 Audiocassettes (Use Tapes copy 2) (Box 20C)
  - Tapes, n.d. (2 boxes) (Box 21)
  - 1974, 1988, 1992, n.d., (2 folders)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1950s-1990s and n.d.
  Transcripts, drafts, and notes of toasts, speeches, remarks, testimony, and addresses given by A. B. Duke. Organizations sponsoring events include: the White House, the Spanish Institute, Overseas Press Club, National Press Club, and the Council of American Ambassadors. Events include White House Department of State functions, commencements, etc. Includes a speech given at Duke University Library in 1979, and remarks as chairman of the Duke Family Association of NC for the Sesquicentennial Founders' Day at Duke, 1988. Also includes testimony given by Duke for the House Foreign Affairs Committee and farewell speeches upon his leaving various ambassadorships. Other recordings of speeches and ceremonies can be found in the Audio, Film, and Video Series.
  - 1969-1968, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1950s-1990s, (11 folders)
  - 1971-1973, (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - ca. 1960s-1980s, n.d., (11 folders)
- Protocol Papers Series, 1961-1965, 1968
  Consists of correspondence and other documents such as event schedules, guest lists, and travel arrangements for various events, most of them centering on visiting foreign dignitaries.
  Arranged alphabetically by country and occasionally by event. For unknown reasons, there are no headings under the letter "F."
  - Afghanistan (Box 24)
  - Algeria
  - Arabian Peninsula
  - Argentina
  - Australia
  - Austria
  - Barbados
  - Bolivia
  - Brazil
  - Burma
  - Burundi
  - Cameroon
  - Canada
  - Chile
  - Costa Rica
  - Dane
  - Ethiopia, (2 folders)
  - Ecuador
  - Germany
  - Great Britain
  - Greece
  - Hawaii
  - Honduras
  - Iceland
  - India
  - Iran
  - Ireland, (2 folders)
  - Israel
  - Italy, (2 folders)
  - Japan
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines: Visit to San Salvador, El Salvador (Box 25)
  - Jordan, (2 folders)
  - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald
    - Trips to Europe, (2 folders)
    - Funeral of, (2 folders)
  - King, Martin Luther (funeral of)
  - Laos
  - Libya
  - Luxembourg
  - MacArthur, Douglas (funeral of)
  - Malagasy Republic
  - Malaysia
  - Mauritania
  - Mauritius
  - Mexico
  - Morocco, (2 folders)
  - New Zealand
  - Norway
  - "Operational Sail"
  - Pakistan
  - Philippines
  - Rwanda
  - Senegal
  - Somali Republic
  - Tanzania
  - Thailand (Box 26)
  - Trinidad
  - Tunisia, (2 folders)
  - Turkey
  - Uganda
  - Venezuela
  - Yugoslavia
  - Miscellany, (2 folders)
- Scrapbooks Series, 1920s-1992
  Bound scrapbooks varying greatly in size, related to A. B. Duke's personal and professional activities. Contents include photographs, clippings, and other printed materials.
  [AS THESE ALBUMS ARE VERY FRAGILE, REFERENCE STAFF MUST BE CONSULTED BEFORE ITEMS ARE USED.]
  - First Plattsburg Training Regiment, 1940 (Box 27)
  - The Dukes (Madrid - Washington), 1968 (Box 28)
  - A. B. Duke, 1956 (Box 29)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 30)
  - Argentina - Spain, 1951 (Box 31)
  - Poland, ca. 1939-1955
  - ca. 1950-51 (Box 32)
  - 1976
  - ca. 1954-1956 (Box 33)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 34)
  - The Statue of Liberty, Ellis Island, and Centennial Commission, 1992 (Box 35)
  - Wedding pictures, etc., ca. 1950s (Box 36)
  - Africa, El Salvador, ca. 1950s (Box 37)
  - 1958 (Box 38)
  - Palomares, Spain, 1966, Jan.17-Apr. 8 (Box 39)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 40)
  - History of the New York City Department of Civic Affairs and Public Events, 1974-1975
  - 1965 (Box 41)
  - 1958 (Box 42)
  - San Salvador (Box 43)
  - A Celebration of the Life of Benjamin Newton Duke, 1979
  - ca. 1920s-1950s (Box 44)
  - Chief of Protocol, 1962 (Box 45)
  - Spain, 1966 (Box 46)
  - 1946-1956 (Box 47)
  - 1950s
  - Chief of Protocol, 1961 (Box 48)
- Pictures Series, ca. 1930s-1990s and n.d.
  Subjects include family, friends, and colleagues of Angier Biddle Duke, as well as many prominent politicians and dignitaries, and celebrities. Subjects can also include events such as the Zellerbach Commission's tour of post-war Europe, and often depict residences and estates. Photographs are either bound in albums or loose in folders. Includes formal photographs as well as many candid shots. There are hundreds of photographs, formal and candid, of the Duke family, and dozens of the Kennedy family.
  Series is unarranged.
  [SOME ALBUMS ARE FRAGILE: REFERENCE STAFF MUST BE CONSULTED BEFORE USING MATERIALS FROM THIS SERIES.]
  - ca. 1950s (Box 49)
  - The Zellerbach Commission: The Commission's Tour of Europe, 1957-Oct.15-Nov. 1
  - Barcelona, n.d. (Box 50)
  - Visit to Headquarters, US Air Forces in Europe, Wiesbaden, Germany, 1967.
  - Africa, n.d.
  - Visit of Antonio Segni, President of Italian Republic to US Atlantic Fleet, Norfolk, Va., 1964, Jan. 16.
  - President John F. Kennedy, n.d.
  - Various members of the Duke family, n.d. (Box 51)
    - Angier Biddle Duke and family, n.d.
    - Angier Biddle Duke, n.d., (2 folders)
    - Robin Chandler (Tippett) Lynn Duke
    - Angier Biddle Duke and Robin Chandler (Tippett) Lynn Duke and their family, n.d., (16 folders)
  - Biddle, Anthony Joseph Drexel, Jr. (Box 52)
  - Bosch, Juan, President of Dominican Rep.
  - Darlington, Charles, and Chester Bowles and Lincoln Gordon
  - Barnes, John; Roger W. Jones
  - Cabot, John M.; George W. Ball
  - Juan Carlos, Prince, King of Spain; Sophia, Princess, Queen
  - Morales, Carrion; Adolphe Berle
  - Carter, James Earl, Jr., and Rosalynn Carter
  - Grand Duchess Charlotte of Luxembourg
  - Chiara, Robert F., President of Panama
  - Chinese artist
  - Wymberley Coerv; Philip Coombs; Harlan Cleveland; William Crockett
  - Crown Prince of Libya
  - Anthony Drexel Biddle and family
  - King of Afghanistan and party in Williamsburg on way to White House
  - Aroesmenu, Carlos Julio, President of Ecuador
  - Kennedy, John F., et. al. and family members
  - Visit of Jacqueline Kennedy to Spain
  - Pell, Claiborne; Angier Biddle Duke; John F. Kennedy
  - Palomares Incident
  - John F. Kennedy Sculptures
  - Klaus, Josef, et al.
  - Kennedy, Jacqueline
  - Angier Biddle Duke; Syrian government; Mrs. Charles A Lindbergh; Henry R. Labouisse; Bert Lance, et al. (Box 52)
  - Archbishop Markarios at Cyprus
  - Togo's Chief of Protocol, Douglas MacArthur II
  - King of Burundi
  - Oholensky, Serge; Wm. Orrick; Wm. Leonhart; Bowles; and Parsons
  - Prosio, Manlio, Secretary General, NATO
  - Dr. Platzer, Austrian Ambassador, presents medal to Mrs. Kennedy
  - Haile Selassie
  - C. B. Johnson
  - Diem, President of South Vietnam
  - Hassan II King of Morocco
  - "Lady Bird" Johnson